[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
welcome to the stoa a digital campfire
where we cohere and dialogue about what
matters most at the nice edge of this
moment um and today at the stoa we have
uh returning back to us sociologist and
political philosopher daniel gertz
in the first or in the second session of
math long residency with us
and um yeah welcome daniel
so just a refresher on the format daniel
will start us off with a presentation
and we will follow it with a q a so if
you have a question for daniel during or
after the presentation just drop it in
the chat box
uh we'll start it if you start it with a
question or a queue then
we can find it easier and remember this
session will be recorded and posted on
youtube so if you would like your
question to be asked
on your behalf just indicate that in the
chat
all right let's get started
hello everyone it's nice to be back um
and good to see some familiar faces from
last time
some new names and some old friends
who are joining who i catch up with
much too little and
uh and also some one or two contacts who
i've known for a long time but never had
the pleasure to
meet so um i considered how to
best use this uh this presentation
given that we set out for these metamark
deep dives
stuff that we're not usually presenting
in the books and the texts on our
website um
stuff that emil and i have been talking
about i've been considering
and exploring on my own
but haven't really integrated into uh
writing books and so on um
and i guess um the the main thing that
makes the meta modern
these different aspects and things is uh
is basically that they're based on the
same
engine or base philosophy right um
so we live in a kind of a renaissance
this was a
very good point uh made by uh by a
friend recently
that um well people make all of these
different
um these different analogies for which
kind of
time we're in i read one article it says
we're in a new actual age
like 2 500 years ago another
says we're in a revolution that's very
common one other says uh we're
in a second modernity
um some people say we're in a new
industrial revolution
we're in a new something and maybe the
best
uh is actually to say we're in a new
renaissance
and um the renaissance had these
renaissance people right but what was so
magical
did you guys hear kids in the background
it's my neighboring kids playing i i'm
gonna
close the window
it's been like this ever since they got
one of those big maps you can jump on
um anyway uh so um
um the uh
[Music]
the renaissance why were there
renaissance people really
well of course of italy that in northern
italy and then the
[Music]
competing states at that time uh
they uh they uh
had maybe twice the gdp of all uh
of anywhere else in the world and uh the
medicis could
uh could pay for be patrons of the arts
and and the sciences and these things
kind of started to flower but
why did pete the same person become both
a scientist
and an artist and a philosopher and
whatnot
in these states well probably it was
because the meta meme
the underlying meta meme was shifting
a new pattern of life in society was
coming within reach and
um this new philosophy or new pattern
allowed for many low-hanging
conceptual fruits to be picked with
er with great ease really
so it became it there was just a lot of
stuff that was easily invented once you
had crossed a certain boundary in
society
that's where i think we are right now so
when once
people start to pick up a more
meta-modern philosophy and view of
life it tends to become fairly easy
to be innovative in different fields
and well in these days in
these early days of these new times
it makes sense to try and
[Music]
try and gather all the little pearls
that we can
and and put them together and like
lay them out and look at them together
and not just look at them really play
with them really try and embody them and
stuff
so um this
um this particular theme i
if we had four teams lined up in the
pipeline so we have um
we had aesthetics in the arts last time
and then we have spirituality
and we have gender and sexuality and
then we have religion
and spirituality in a way is close to
religion so
i the original idea was to take that
as a third but it made more sense in a
way to do it as the second
and the reason um is that
actually it connects beautifully to
aesthetics there's a there's a
nice bridge between the aesthetics of
the arts and spirituality on one hand
and on the other hand we can do
more fun stuff um and get into
some more visceral stuff i guess in the
sexuality
gender part if we have spirituality
covered first
so i have a powerpoint presentation um
for you we might not have the time to go
through all of it
if we do all the better i will start i
will
share my screen by the way
share screen there we go
and uh powerpoint
from the beginning
today's talk is simply called modern
spirituality
dive into the subtle and beyond
so let's start with that what is
spirituality
one way of grasping it
is that it has to do with subjective
states
now subjective states as we discuss in
the first hansi book
is not reducible to emotions
they're how we feel as a whole
or as a totality the entirety
of our suchness or being
or our feminine phenomenology at any
given
point in time so stop and consider these
words
some of you might recognize this list
magnificence majesty
vastness greatness
splendor love
joy clarity
openness
compassion
certitude flow
jubilation playfulness
fullness enlightenment
lightness
peace
presence
power realness
humility freedom
creation freshness
birth wonder
victory serenity
divinity purity
meaning unity
union communion
uniqueness chosenness
awe fulfillment
insight grace
refinement subtlety
simplicity
simplicity gratefulness
substance radiant
emptiness
so there's
i guess not all of these um are
resonate with all of us
but hopefully each of us can get a sense
of some of them right
we like what what does magnificence feel
like
it's not quite correct to say that
magnificence is an emotion
and nor would it be it would be quite a
reduction to say
that all of these things like is
magnificent is it
happiness well they're positive one
sense or another right
let's see um
they're positive uh in one sense or
another
uh but they're not
um they're not in
in and of themselves happiness right
they are high states there are different
different experiences that we can have
within the range of high
states
now
so so there is a thread to them they're
all positive experiences in some
way but they're all quite subtle and
difficult
to to name and grasp and point out and
um and they're fairly rare
unfortunately we would like to have
lives imbued with all of these qualities
and we would wish for one another
on a good day that
these qualities uh
were manifested in the lives of others
so that's just to get at
what spirituality really really is
it has to do with these high state
qualities we'll get to this in a moment
so there is a connection here between
these qualities and
and the aesthetic that we discussed last
time so aesthetic as we discussed
often comes first in a metameme
or the arts they tend to breach the
boundaries
long long before the metabeam becomes
conscious
ideas and ideals and
much much less
manifest structures of society and
much less norms in society and embodied
experience of the people
so there is something about all of these
states
which link it intuitively to the
aesthetic and
it is that the aesthetic always whether
it's
a rain dance or um
paintings of animals on a cave on a cape
wall
or the ceiling of a mighty temple
they all grasp for something intuitive
for something expressive
which you still cannot express correctly
in words which is
outside of the symbolic word word
world and somehow points at the sacred
at something you wouldn't want to ruin
something
that innately grabs your respect
um and of course they have to do with
the right hemisphere stuff
um in the brain this
famous master in the hem and the
emissary
um division of a right and left brain or
conceptual brain and a more
intuitive um aesthetic
holistic sensing brain
and they all relate to somehow
expressing a depth to existence
something that is beyond
the obvious something
either in the direction of beauty which
is of course the the most obvious
expression of aesthetics but also um
truth-seeking or mystery as uh as this
kind of depth this should actually be
called
or tragedy that you care about
the brokenness of the world and and
inherent suffering of being and beings
in the world
um so
all of the aesthetic movements have come
from the um from frequenting
from frequenting these higher states
somehow there's a connection between
reaching into these higher states and
being in a
sense of intuitive wholeness and
expressing that on in the world
as aesthetics and that you can do
before you actually formalize the idea
and you don't have to be many people to
do it it's enough that it happens within
one artist and then it comes out as some
kind of
cultural innovation or expression
which is why you then express
often things that are beyond the
confines of your time
or your society and you can reach into
later value memes or emerging value
means
that you haven't been fed as a kid
and i mean there are clear examples of
this um
if we look at the the
um these qualities again like subtlety
and
it take a child musical g's like uh
billy eilish for instance so uh billy
eilish
she's from california i guess and uh
and she expresses um a lot of like
well in in her lyrics and stuff a lot of
things that are
um well much too mature for for
for a kid like that uh and if you ask
her or if
interviewers ask her about it she just
says well i just felt like it
but if you look at her on stage you
notice there's a subtlety to her
movements
um which i i can't really uh i can't
really embody that myself but but she
follows the music
very very very subtly and and uh she
gets into these high states
and from there she can download the
outer reaches
of our culture and then express it in a
way that makes a lot of people feel
stuff
and that's why it's so big right
yeah so so that's just to point out the
bridge here
but now we're delving into spirituality
itself
so we've already kind of said this um
there's a scale of subjective states
and uh i didn't make this picture myself
a friend made it eric newton he's uh his
um
therapist in uh in new orleans and he
actually uses these states in his
uh it's uh from the states are from our
books
um but uh
uh but he uses this in his uh therapy
and actually he has spread this to a
group of four therapists and
from what i hear it's actually been
revolutionizing their practice
because they can they get a skill which
is much more
specific than just saying how are you on
a scale from one to ten which is always
relative and people will say well i
guess a seven
um you name some qualities um
and the idea of these subjective states
is simply that
at any time it'll feel like something to
be you
so uh well thomas nagle um
famously asked what is it like to be a
bat
in this likely it is like something can
be a bad
um but being is never indifferent
there's always a sense of good or bad
to it um and uh
on most
in most of our time that we're alive
will be actually at the state seven or
most of us
um or plus minus a couple of states here
these are the states of everyday life as
it were
um so um
like and to be very honest unfortunately
we're not
normally in a uh on any
day of the week most people will not be
at eight
satisfied with everything just just a
basic okayness
um we'll tend to have
some little unease somewhere in our
system especially if we're adults
because we'll have uh we'll have
um accumulated with so many little
traumas and hurts and insecurities and
worries that there's always something
and nagging us a little bit and now and
then
that'll let go and we're in a higher
state satisfied everything is just
genuinely okay
like life's supposed to be but then to
be honest we also
quite often fall down below
uh the the seven and we're
at um
and and we're at um uneasy
we're genuinely feeling some unease or
some like something that affects us
that in a way that that we can tell that
uh well we're a little bit out of it
we're
we have a headache we're a bit tired
etc etc and we can go to very uneasy so
we have
real anxiety going on but then we're
still in the
in the scope of what everyday life
usually feel like
feels like so 99 of us 99
of the time are going to be in these
middle range states
very uneasy uneasy somewhat uneasy
satisfied lively but
but somewhere along somewhere around
lively like life doesn't really get
better
than that normal life doesn't so
i mean you'll be at the party
and just for once everything is perfect
you some some friends you wouldn't know
were there
uh surprise you uh you're getting a very
nice flow
you just feel genuinely alive and
you just feel happy to be connected with
people you're having
fun all worries are gone gone gone but
there is something beyond that and
not all people experience these higher
states that are beyond that
and they will genuinely not believe
that they exist but they do and that's
why
spirituality is real because
spirituality in this definition
is simply that which
corresponds to these
four highest states so
what happens if your heart blows open
and you feel joyous and full of light
maybe
maybe in a moment where you're deeply in
love
and you actually get it to work you
actually get
whoever you're deeply in love with
wonderful
wow and like it's
it's like something in reality itself
shifts right
or you're super super inspired
by a deep deep purpose and you
contemplate on it and how you can make
this happen in your life and you open up
there's a sense of vastness or obliges
just openness just clarity
and that's really as far as my
my own spiritual experience would go um
but we do know that there are saints and
sages
um and well maybe not in the moral sense
i'd be agnostic about that or highly
skeptical about it but
but but there are people who experience
a profound love for all
that is and a lot of people have these
experiences in
psychedelic in psychedelic context of
course
there are also experiences of
enlightenment just full
super being or whatever um and for most
people it's
again only on dmt trips etc but um
um but but these are possible
so what i mean when i say spirituality
is whatever pertains to
these highest states these states that
are
beyond um
that are beyond what we experience in
everyday life
um and they um
they can be
expressed in life and that is also then
spirituality
so it's spirituality is nurturing these
states
getting to know them growing the
capacity
to be in these states transmitting these
states
and expressing these states through
for instance artistic work but it can be
through other things as well it can be
through service
[Music]
there's bhakta yoga for instance it can
be through
it can be through truth seeking it can
be through a purpose a divine purpose
or through the spiritual practice itself
[Music]
and and there's like a real
there's a real difference there
because fundamentally what does it mean
to be
spiritual it means to have some kind of
relationships to these states right
so you can be religious but not
spiritual it can be spiritual but not
religious but i'm not too fond of that
distinction as as we'll get to in
like hopefully in a future episode
um but um
we can
um yeah the the the
terrible or the tragic part is that
since these states are so rare
and maybe only manifest the minority of
the population
and if they do it manifest they can do
so rarely
do it so rarely that people actually
forget about it then
um most people won't believe
in spirituality so so they say i don't
believe in god i don't believe in
religions
but it's a terrible baby to be throwing
out with the bathwater
that you're also throwing out
spirituality which is
in terms of without saying anything
about the ontological
um the ontological
presuppositions that you have about
reality or anything like that
[Music]
but it is real that people have these
experiences
and if in that sense spirituality is
real
and most people won't believe it and
nevertheless we may need
that spirituality and we may need to
garner its forces and harness its forces
to um to resolve a lot of the
issues of our time and the challenges
and to have the best possible lives
um so one way
of grasping this is in the term
of cosmo eroticism so
um cosmo eroticism means
falling in love with life or it means
um loving the experience
or suchness or isness of life itself
and i thus placed it on a
sort of hierarchy that
eroticism is actually at the center
um wilbur and others have recently been
talking about
they've talking about growing up and
showing up
and waking up for a while
and cleaning up but they've recently
added a fifth it's called
opening up and it particularly
corresponds to this to this
eroticism to um
to feeling truly alive
to genuinely enjoying
the experience of things
so meta-modern spirituality
accepts that spirituality exists
and then posits that me eroticism
and the falling in love with life
is a primary goal and this is actually a
primary goal
before compassion and even before
transcendence this is important because
look at it how much
is our compassion worth let's say i
meditate
on the suffering of others and
i try to be compassionate but my own
life
does not have that fullness of
experience
it it's gonna be almost all but
impossible for me
to wish for a fullness of the heart and
of experience
and and the love of life if i don't have
it myself
so it's like a foundation for compassion
in turn transcendence going beyond the
self and going beyond
any particular identification and going
beyond
any worldly desires
in turn needs to build on both
erraticism
and compassion because
well let's say i have a transcendent
goal
but i let it override simple compassion
or relatedness
to you well
then i'm it's that that would be a
pretty severe form of
of spiritual bypassing
so we have to in this
way of grasping spirituality where we're
centering out the higher states
which are always experienced by the
experiencer
we have to focus on this cosmo eroticism
first we have to create
this fullness of life
so that leaves us with a work of
spiritual awakening which is
somewhat different i suppose from
just meditating uh and uh
going for that transcendence or or just
cultivating that compassion
also worthy goals but maybe not where
where the core should be of the
spiritual project
erotic in this sense of course life
force
aliveness carnality power and power is a
positive thing it means
to create and as we said creation always
as i said in the last episode
creation always implies destruction
so so the power to decide over life and
death or what exists or not but
everybody wants
power over their own life
and we don't like to be powerless and we
want to feel
empowered there are of course
a lot of uh a lot of bad ways this can
show up
and if if our ira if our erotic
core is frustrated
energetic flows that we feel
alive in our bodies we just feel that we
can breathe
that we can feel a fullness of existence
lightness presence
and in a sense just an advanced very
general sense happiness
but why aren't i mean and we all know
this from when we were little kids
uh before we had accumulated enough
trauma
uh that at least sometimes christmas
would really really really really feel
like christmas
uh well sorry if this doesn't apply to
you personally but i'm sure you can find
some
um some corresponding experience but
i if i go back to early childhood
memories i remember here
um like on uh when
when christmas was nearing up and when
this was when i was four or
something and i just look at the redness
of one of those
uh christmas shiny christmas balls
and it's just like my whole existence is
just flow
overflowing with this loving um
um just this mood
or sense that it's so real that
christmas is happening for instance
but then of course we we get worn out we
have seen them in
the same experiences before um
we have uh apprehensions because we know
there are there are risks when we open
up
um so so we're blocked by all sorts of
traumas
all sorts of little wounds all sorts of
contradictions within ourselves
so to get to the higher states
we need to of course practice on those
or or create
opportunities and situations and rituals
and the rest of that
but we primarily need to heal our cosmo
erotic core
which cannot ignore things like
sexuality and just our
will and want to be happy
so looking closer at that trauma
um so in um
in integral circles they they use these
um these four
bodies as they call them from the
um which are imported from from uh
new religion really and and uh and uh
mystical practices
and they call them the gross body which
would be like
just the sense that i have like i'm
sitting on the chair
um i uh um
i can feel a little bit dry in my mouth
because i'm speaking
i can feel a certain tension here and
there
but it's it's obvious that the gross
body is obvious
in every moment however
there's a lot lot more going on
if i if we examine it a little bit more
closely
so if you look at beyond the gross body
you have all these flows
of emotions and feelings and moods
that are also just in subtler sense
bodily sensations
they're just not as obvious um and they
and they
you wouldn't necessarily be able to
locate them in your body
um sometimes you can
uh so so maybe right now if i look in i
can
feel well there's a little bit of
nervousness
going on but i i mean that's my way of
naming it but there's like a very very
subtle sense of
tension there is uh
there is a a bit of eagerness pressing
on
there is a bit of like focus and
concentration
and all of these things are going on at
the same time now
beyond that there is another layer
of experience which is how
the whole of reality around myself
is felt at this particular moment
so that is what's called the causal body
and um so
and then and here i mean the language
really breaks down it really breaks down
you can't name it but for me for
instance it's like
there's a bit of a crack up there and
you can kind of sense
i can sense the whole thing is a little
bit wobbly but it's
at the same time it's it's big and open
and sometimes it feels contracted like
jail
and you could go beyond that i can go
into
the non-dual realm which is that just
the quality of business or suchness or
being or i am-ness itself
uh and all of those these
are always ever present now it's mistake
actually i would say
to call them bodies because it misleads
the reader um what they are
in my vocabulary is they are layers
of phenomenology phenology phenomenology
being
the direct experience of the now the
phenomena as they show up in first
person experience
and there are different layers of depth
to that phenomenology
some obvious and in the foreground
and others less obvious and in the
background
but here's the crux they become more
significant to our inner states
the deeper we go so
for instance let's say i feel totally at
peace the world feels big and vast and
open
and i have no fear and
and everything just flows beautifully
through my body
but i have a terrible tummy ache
will i be unhappy will i be suffering
no the gross body
suffers but it is within
the larger embrace of the subtle body
and the causal body
which are healed and at peace and in
that
in that case i don't really suffer
likewise you can turn this around you
can say
um you can say that um
we're at a party we're having fun
we're eating wonderful cake we're
drinking the best whiskey ever
but we feel empty inside and there's
something nagging at us
and we feel unsure about
whether reality is a good or bad place
or even
maybe we have a profound existential
fear whether or not this is reality at
all
which would be a pathology at the
non-dual
level um
and of course these relate and then of
course i'm not happy
in any profound or deeper sense
so there there's an increasing
um scale here of
what we might want to address
as we delve deeper into spirituality and
then
um the higher states have to do of
course
with movements which are harmonic
and in resonance at the higher at the
deeper
layers of
phenomenology um so and
and they're ever present but to notice
them is a kind of involution
so when we're kids we're just really
aware
of the gross body and the other things
just kind of are in the background
um but then we can be better and better
at
become better and better recognizing and
seeing
and responding to the qualities present
within those other deeper layers
and that's a kind of involution then
that we
that we kind of um
it's a subject object thing we kind of
um extract ourselves
from the concreteness of one experience
and see the the the
larger subtler experience within which
that arises
so trauma often
very often has to do with a subtle body
um very often it has to do with
um with just
our hearts tensing up on a subtle level
and then never fully opening to
happiness never fully opening to love
never fully opening to an erotic
exchange
under fully opening um to the joy of a
friendship
to the beauty of a wilderness um site
to the intuition of a work or a purpose
that we're
that we're trying to manifest in our
lives
we're blocked kind of let's see
so how what do these blocks feel like
now we get into
if we go a few previous here
now we go into the lower states here
um the ones that are below the
experience of everyday life
where which are nightmarish
and which we also fairly rarely
experience but that's also
the the seriousness of reality
um so reality is a cosmic joke but it's
also very very very dead serious and the
real
reason it is very very dead serious is
because of the real potential and
ever-present
potential of the lower states so that
the
existence of the lower states sets us up
for
uh very very very high stakes
in life and in existence and in the
universe which is why we have to
be religious about the universe um or
and our place in it because we have to
take
into account that hell exists for real
um so going into these lower states i'm
going to go through them a little bit
faster than the other ones
then the last one we look at all these
experiences
anxiety honest
rage hatred bitterness
imprisonment slavery
humiliation loss
loneliness meaninglessness
unrealness confusion
boredom filth torture
oppression suffocation unsettlement
darkness dead meat rot
painful emptiness powerlessness
heaviness uncertainty
grossness or grassness
hopelessness on life half-life
screaming woundedness suffering
unbearable pain complication
terror explosiveness i guess
at the very core of all of this is
terror
if if you look at the highest
at the worst uh low states
like you're in hell
it's going to be something like
um it's not just going to be that you're
unhappy
and feel oh no i have to end my life is
going to be
that you feel trapped in an
in a corridor or an endless
or an endless loop which you can never
get out of
and people have religious experiences
including dark nights of the soul
where they also open up to
the existence of the ever presence of
these lower states
that's actually about as far as we go in
the books i'm sorry
but there's something there's something
of course
[Music]
wrong about placing this these all on
one
scale because
um in everyday life we
we have the normal states and then we
can go beyond
that to the higher states but also to
the lowest states
and the lowest states once we encounter
them
and go through them we're often
catapulted up to a high state and this
is
in
george and buddhism for instance or or
tibetan buddhism you have all these
pictures of
a monster which you face up and then it
becomes up
and then becomes a saint or your friend
or or
an angel of some sort um
and the the monster is illusory
uh but nevertheless it's there and you
have to go through it
um so
we have seen that well we suffer more
when something is wrong on when we have
pathologies or constrictions on the
deeper layers of phenomenology
now um
if we then zoom in on these states and
we look at
wilbur's four quadrants again um
and this is yeah it gets a bit theory
um heavy but if you zoom in on the
states
themselves then you can actually use the
same heuristic of the
four quadrants
which well i guess a lot of people have
have
have some uh background knowledge about
that
and you can divide it up into its
qualities
so at the upper left which is the inner
experience itself of the inner
experience itself
that there is the state itself so uh
it's
something going on at the gross level at
the gross level at the subtle level
at the causal level or at the non-dual
level so we notice that the lower states
also seem to be
at the causal level or the subtle level
or the non-dual level for instance
um it's not enough to just have a tummy
ache to be in hell
um but beyond that
if we look then at the social part the
social quadrant
of the inner experience there is a
content
of what goes on within each of these
layers of phenomenology
at each time so we have
um well in the gross body i'll have
any number of sensations that i can name
or not name
or not be able to name but i mean i see
the light around me
i feel the chair i have
emotions which pertain more to the
subtle body
i have the flows all of these relate to
something all of these have
directionality
and of course stuckness we'll get back
to that in a moment
a third quality of the state
is the capacity to observe
and recognize the state within myself
so this is the eye of the eye we can
also develop in that
so you can we can develop in the gross
subtle causal non-dual states themselves
we can develop in the content of those
states and fix the different flows that
are within them
but to do so we must be able to
recognize
those states within ourselves which is a
capacity in and of itself
and then to do something about it we get
to what corresponds to the systemic
to the systemic quadrant uh how things
how different objects relate to one
another there is the
agency the capacity
to change the content of the states
and or to traverse uh the different
layers
and or to steer our um
our inner
eye of the eye so to speak um so
we can different people can be
differently developed
in all of these four quadrants of
states so some people can have
um a much richer causal
state experience but they can maybe not
recognize that's what's going on in them
others are good at recognizing all
that's going on in them but
the inside is still a mess some people
are good at reorganizing
themselves um and and maybe
locking up stuff or or untying knots
affecting their own state
um so that kind of actually breaks down
this one-dimensional
um theory that we have in the book but
the book
of course was not primarily about
transpersonal psychology and
spirituality was about
politics and societies we wanted to go
on a little bit quicker before
we went too deep into this context into
this
topic um but a lot of people who are you
know more on the spiritual side or high
depth people
have reacted that well it does feel a
little bit shallow and they're not wrong
um it is because these um
these distinctions are not made there
so that this doesn't make sense
that a state is higher if just
because it's happier or more pleasurable
not necessarily then i mean again
we have to travel to really really enjoy
the cake we have to enjoy it
at the subtle level as well not just on
the call
on the gross level
um
yeah so our task
as spiritual seekers is to help one
another and ourselves
to develop these four capacities in
relation to one another
um develop um
the the real experience of of the
deeper and deeper layers of
phenomenology
recognize the ability to recognize and
self-reflect
to see the content and what is going on
because the content of our experience is
always relational that's why it
is there and it's always in movement
always in a flow
and it is um then ultimately
about transforming those experiences
now stuckness is important here what is
stuckness
in in the cause and the subtle body
stuckness in the causal body is
basically when two flows
conflict with each other so you have
maybe one flow
to protect yourself and to assert
yourself
and you have one flow to open up and oh
and and submit yourself to the
vulnerability
of being deeply um
deeply present with another person but
these two conflict
so what happens when you have one
flow of experiences
that are trying to do one thing at the
same time something else is going on
within your vast inner landscape
that is pushing against that well
you get self-intense i mean i've done a
bunch of
uh something called rosen therapy um
and it's uh where they touch your body
and uh
let you and they kind of support you
with little
with their hands and and
get these muscles to relax and it's
what i found was in that therapy work
was that there
i was walking around with a shitload of
tensions
in my chest that
exactly correlated to my inability
to open up to romantic love how about
that
and that caused a ton load of problems
in my life but it wasn't easy
to spot and once i had spotted it and i
could
like recognize wait a minute i can
actually push here and i notice it's
like a needle
uh and i can push here and
um but going from there to actually
doing something about it
also took a lot of time and work and
actually still
still ongoing but here here is again
we're talking about the opening up part
a lot cosmo eroticism
something is stopping us or blocking us
from being fully
in life fully engaged across the layers
of phenological experience
[Music]
oh yeah stuckness in the subtle body two
subjectively felt flows collide and
block one another
untied the subtle body changes is freed
and that's what we can mean with an open
heart
that the the heart allows itself
as it were to smile
[Music]
so um actually
the chakras but also i mean there are
all sorts of versions of this
um i i like the chakras because they're
so simple
um of course um
a lot of ink has been spilled to say
that the chakras oh they're
they're real they're not real uh
there's no uh physiological
correspondence to them
um but again that that discussion misses
the point
the point is uh
these didn't grow from the study of the
body
the gross body or the medical body or
the biological body
um they
and they grew from
exploration of subjective experience
more specifically
uh subjective experience of um
um of the subtle body
so just as so i think they still present
a good map for us to see
what we need to open up and they also
subtly guide us from the grass
towards the cause of the non-dual
in a chakra meditation for instance if
you
work very diligently through
all of these energy centers you can
begin at the root chakra
and until you can kind of feel it and
you kind of
feel some flow through it then you go on
to the
sacral chakra at the below below the
navel in the belly
you go on until uh
until some there's a smile there
until there's a smile at the bottom of
the belly
and i think a lot of people can can
relate to that
and that when when you're like generally
happy there's just a little smile on
your belly you know
and you can go on to the solar plexus
chakra you can feel like
a certain will or a fire or power
and and these things often also reflect
our experi
our personalities like this really
assertive guy
sit down meditate with him he won't feel
a lot in any of the chakras but he'll
feel
he'll feel this one very strong like
it's overflowing
heart chakra of course feeling
compassion
feeling love compassion feels like hurt
but it feels like good hurt
um throat chakra
things are getting more subtle this is
what actually i meditated on before i
got on this call
has to with expressiveness truth seeking
things that can't really be proven
but intuitively felt we kind of make
sense that
we don't want to say something we kind
of tense up a little bit here
something gets stuck quite literally in
our throat
we it doesn't flow through us the
communication doesn't flow
third eye chakra um
well then we're getting into stuff like
when you feel into that kind of thing
uh you generally don't feel exactly some
sensations in your body you almost feel
outside of your body crown chakra you
work through the whole thing
you a lot of meditations start there and
they say
start looking at this little
spot on the top of your head and
after a while you tend to be catapulted
away
from all thoughts and and the body and
now this
only rarely happens to me i'm not a
super meditator myself
uh but i do have this experience so you
work through all of them
and then it's like you jump off a cliff
and
you just plunge down into darkness it
can
be pretty scary because you you worry
that you can't actually get back
um daniel uh just letting you know that
we're at the top of the hour
okay okay thank you uh so anyway i do
feel that the chakras
um it can be used in this way as a kind
of checklist
for our subtle body uh
for our subtle body work
and but just meditating on them
and just feeling in on them usually
doesn't do
what it i mean all the necessary stuff
so we might need
um somatic therapy
we might need we might need
different forms of therapy like just
talk therapy and
freudian stuff and figure out who were
really
mad at when we were kids and how we felt
belittle and and powerless and stuff
but by and large to get to these higher
states
um and to frequent them more often and
to express them in our lives
and to do so in a healthy manner we need
to somehow
unlock and open up at on all of these
levels and and they're of course good to
practice
in sexual relationships um that you can
it makes sense to before
uh while making love for instance uh
before
you uh focus entirely on on like
opening up your heart chakra to the
person uh
you're sharing an experience with
uh it can make more sense to work
downwards and up until you can
and all orgasms and stuff they actually
work the same way that
you can almost feel that it's like one
of those things you hit
and then in a theme park
where you can go where it goes higher uh
depending on how hard you hit so if you
have
better subtle body flows throughout
throughout these
then the orgasm can go higher and it can
feel
romantic and overflowing or it can even
um it can even feel cosmic um
but it it depends on these opening up
opening ups uh i'll hopefully say more
about this
because i make it sound so cute and it's
not um
but yeah but but in the
in the next session i'll hopefully get
back to this
so this distinction has become very
popular lately citric and tantric
i want to connect true to it um
i want to connect to it in this
model that we're presenting here
um so sutrix spirituality um
is more like the classical buddhism
thing uh
you meditate you have the sutras you
follow
a certain code and you purify your soul
you get away from from the grass
uh and and focus instead on the causal
and you kind of and there's a
relationship there than that you go
vikasa meditation for instance is has
been called causal mental
causal body meditation as well which is
based on classical buddhism
um so um um
[Music]
and and in in these meditations you
might do things like
well you um
imagine a rotting body you imagine death
you you realize that the gross body
isn't it there is actually a causal body
underlying it
um or no not body layer of
layer of phenomenology and if you can
resonate and gain harmony with that
even a tummy ache won't destroy your day
where uh i mean but there are risks of
course without its uh
life negating um and there's the unhappy
buddhist
syndrome meaning that um like
buddhists are actually less happy than
uh
other religious followers which is
quite contrary to to popular belief
and this is of course because they've
been taught uh a religion or world view
which
says that the world is suffering and uh
the only way is to get out of it um
but this isn't of course true of the
minority who are practitioners
within buddhism and dedicate their lives
to this they tend to be
unusually happy but as
as a as a doctrine it's not necessarily
very
life affirmative now tantric buddhism
and tantric spirituality
puts cosmeroticism at the center as i
have suggested here as well
and it works more through the subtle
body
and goes from the subtle body to
non-dual spirituality so it also reaches
deeper and it's often than more esoteric
and smaller groups and more radical
but of course if you're dealing with
tantric practices um and you're dealing
with this kind of
uh with this kind of work that has to do
with
um engaging with life
and saying yes to all of that those
experiences
um then you well there's the risk of
erratic seduction or there the risk of
getting attached to desirable or
positive experiences
in the subtle body and this can develop
into crazy sex cults as
it usually does
oh yeah and that's actually as far as i
got in the presentation so
uh um yeah um
we can say more about transpersonal
perspective on this but the idea of a
trans personal perspective is basically
there's more detail to it but i just
want to say that
that we
create these spaces for one another
so it's the more
tantric we go the more social it gets
the more social it gets um um
yeah speaking as a sociologist
spirituality is social
it's a social enterprise because it's
about the relatedness to reality
and we need and we always relate through
and via and
between one another and so
um like
we cannot and should not uh view this
as uh like the separate
paths of different uh individuals
um again this this goes back to tantric
and
and stuff um and going from uh
going to mayan of buddhism and stuff but
[Music]
but the idea is that
you meet a person all four layers
are interacting at the same time
and we need to address the interactions
of all of those four layers and create a
spiritually
rich society that would be
a meta-modern spiritual goal
that we together create rituals
practices
norms understandings relationships
which strengthen this rich field
of the different layers of our
interconnected
um of our interconnected uh
layers of of uh existence or
phenomenology and
the deeper we go there the more intimate
it gets
and the more social it gets
so i mean fixing a tummy ache is about
me
it's not about peter but
fixing um wounds from childhood and
projection patterns back and forth
and opening up our hearts to one another
is actually
it's it's it happens between us so we
can and should focus
in our spiritual work always on the
trans person
and that's where i'll end thank you very
much
happy to take questions awesome thanks
so much daniel
uh so we've got a couple of questions
actually
from rob had a few really interesting
ones do you want to
start us off rob sure thank you daniel
that was
wonderful um so the
the question i wanted to bring up was
really related to this um
this dichotomy between sutrick and
tantric
um streams of thought i think about
spiritual practice but
uh there's a pattern that ken wilber
points out um
in a lot of his work i think it comes up
in in brief history of
everything and uh he talks about the
difference between
the transcendent stream which i think
relates to the sutrick
um of sort of up and out of the body up
and out of
of gross experience and toward the sort
of transcendental plane
and then the imminent stream and he
relates these to
and the eminent would be like sort of
down into the body down into embodiment
into the gross and the physical um and
he relates these to like transcendent
being masculine and
imminent being feminine which uh
goes back to sort of the history of of
like uh
matriarchal cultures versus patriarchal
cultures and how they celebrated
spirituality and
there's there's something in the in the
process of going
through a tran transformation
spiritually that looks to me like it
needs both of these streams
but interestingly in like past uh
cultural
value memes like pre-modern up through
modernism there was a real preference
for masculine
streams or for the sutra or transcendent
stream and a real
um allergy almost to the feminine and
a lot of you know pre-modern religions
where like if you banish the body and
punish the like physical drives and
stuff then you'll transcend and you'll
you'll awaken um whereas like
emerging into post-modernity there's a
whole lot more of like
banish the masculine and prefer the
feminine
um kind of reaction um to that process
and a little bit of a sort of um
maybe we'd call it a like archaic
revivalism
but like archaic in the sense of like
pre-transcendent masculine back when
there was just a lot more embedded like
sort of magical thinking kind of
approach to um spirituality so in
my question then is how does the
metamodern meme
treat these two streams and
um and the like other value memes and
their reactions to them how is
how does metamodernism like approach
that
so so there um there's a lot
there there are a lot of um ways to um
[Music]
um to work with with this issue
um i guess um
well i'll say a couple of things uh one
thing is
and just on a very basic level we have
hard value means or or metamines
and soft values or metamines and
the hard ones generally come together
with um
a material revolution um or
in the revolution of industry and
transport and information
so um and they tend to fulfill the
ethics
of the former which was a critique of
the
two steps forward so so we have
i mean animism which is
a fairly soft value mean
and quite embodied and so on and
um well
going from there you have you have what
i call faustianism
red which is fairly hard and
masculine from there on you actually
have if you look
not at the teachings of the church later
on but you look at the core
uh teachings of jesus or buddha or
whatever
they would criticize power relations and
they were these religions were actually
popular with women so uh
and so buddhism for instance uh
worked to um to have buddhist nuns
uh join join the sangha for instance and
well christianity would
say that well sure render unto caesar
what belongs to him
but in the end at the end of the day um
well you should govern because you're
just not because you're powerful
right uh and then you have uh
modernism which is quite masculine it
takes up all of the all of the things
that were in the ethics of
post-pasteurism or the critique of
faustianism
so it says okay sure we won't have
slaves i'm sure we're equals
but from that basis or setting we're
going to
we're going to express ourselves we're
create stuff out in the world then you
have a feminine
critique of that or soft critique of
that in post-modernism and of course
if you look at the demographics of today
the developmental demographics and the
cultural demographics
uh you have a high prevalence of women
in post-modernism so meta-modernism
comes in at a point where the masculine
reasserts itself again
um and and
with with terms such as or with with the
slogans such as
after re deconstruction reconstruction
must follow
uh or protosynthesis or
sincere irony and um
that it wants to create something again
and wants to
out compete the modern world in many
ways right
so so in terms of spirituality then
uh metamodernism uh is a little bit more
on the masculine side
and if you look at what i have proposed
here
it doesn't exactly i mean of course i'm
gonna
i'm gonna agree with wilbur that
and then with yourself that we need
both transcendence and and uh and
both the transcenders and the uh
ascenders
no the ascenders and the descenders yes
um and and they need to kind of meet in
this cosmic dance
now what i try to do here uh
is still a kind of meta-modern
synthesis that attempts at least to
uh achieve that end if you look at
this one for instance uh it connects
to the states um that
it goes from the the more grow
gross to towards the more uh
subtle towards the more transcendent
uh but uh it tries
to make sure that
um we
we always do our homework
and go through all of that those low
states
to make sure that eroticism is at the
core
but the goal is still transcendence
so the goal is still transcendence
through
a second layer of compassion we're just
what we're worried about are these
colonizations
of either force of the other
so we don't want eroticism colonizing
the transcendent then we're stuck in
with adida and he's gonna your
wives
which he literally did and
we don't want compassion
[Music]
we don't want compassion trumping
transcendence
we just wanted to undergird it
and we don't want a transcendence
to empty out life of eroticism
and compassion which easily happens
and a lot of people who start meditating
and
like in the 70s and the 80s tm was huge
right
so a lot of people went to tm uh
transcendental meditation
and they sat down and they did their
mantras
and they had trans transcendent
experiences
and this stuff actually activates a lot
of a lot of your
i just learned this the other day
actually that it activates or
default networks so so it's like
daydreaming on steroids and you you can
reach farther in your thoughts and
creativity if done correctly
but what a lot of people experienced
instead
was that they just felt emptied out
and they just felt kind of numb to
experience and they felt their
creativity
was killed and then they stop doing
transcendental meditation and then they
join whatever pentecostal church is
nearest
because there people are singing people
are happy
and then before you know it they're back
at uh you know a crazy version of uh
post fostering spirituality and they're
literally believing in miracles and
stuff
uh and they pick up a lot of patriarchal
crazy stuff that has to do with that
value
um so um um
the the the marriage of the transcendent
and the descendant is basically that we
always start
with the descendant um and
move upwards and
whenever we don't we end up doing
spiritual bypassing and
and i mean maybe maybe that's fine
if you're living a monk life and
you really really really pay the huge
price that it is
to live a secret life fully
um but then um
well there's obvious all of those forces
are still going to be there right
you're still going to be mad at your dad
sexually frustrated and whatnot
and we do have all of these sexual abuse
problems in all of these churches
um um and congregations
so it appears as though like we need
this fountainhead of life this cosmere
eroticism
for the transcendence to occur in a
healthy
manner and yeah and i
feel at least like that
there's it still asserts
the goal of transcendence but it does so
in a hierarchical manner which is then
again a more as in a more a center
way and i'm sure there's going to be
future forms of spirituality
or future views on spirituality which
will turn this on its head again
but that's how these things evolve
awesome rob do you have any follow up
with that
thanks that was great
okay so uh i feel like um
christian sawyer had an interesting
question uh to
follow after this one christian do you
wanna mute and ask daniel your question
can you hear me which question i put two
in there
feel free to choose okay um
i'll ask both and i'll let daniel choose
then um
the first is why does the tantric path
tend towards
this cult like bs and is there
another way to contain or manage that
process of surrendering into the
eroticism which doesn't rely upon
the external framework of the cult or
the guru
and then the other question is
isn't it also possible to work from
transcendence to eroticism or to do a
lot of back and forth
where the transcendence you know the the
kind of
spaciousness detachment gives one
the freedom to approach the the wounds
the
traumas that are keeping them from
touching into their eroticism uh so that
they can heal them and then
you know get more deeply in touch with
just their spontaneous
creativity yes very very good
um so i'm gonna have to try to answer
both because they're so important so so
the first
one um why and
well there's a gen there's the general
cult mechanism
which uh which we do which we uh
describe in our first hansi book and
it's uh
it says basically that whenever we try
to create hierarchies
on uh not on complexity or code
like not on stuff that is visible and
content but on object banana subjective
experiences oh
this we should be listening to this uh
guy or woman
because we imagine that they have these
inner experiences which we can
verify and then sooner or later
um like it doesn't really mix like
social hierarchies
and subjective experiences because we
can never verify them
so people will be tempted to and be
socially pressured
a little bit lie about what
experience they're actually having at
the moment
and uh and being roles where they
are expected to embody a certain kind of
uh
being or or suchness and so on and these
things
vary a lot and people have ups and downs
and and well
and and then of course there's nothing
about a person
just because they happen to frequent
high states and
and develop great depth which we haven't
talked about a lot today
that makes them write about other topics
it just
gets them this intuition maybe they can
have uh
be more proficient at getting other
people into higher states but
they're not right about other things
right and
nothing is a stronger experience than
the states themselves
so when somebody gets you into a high
state
uh not least in a very vulnerable place
which has to do with sexuality
then you you
naturally experience that this person is
awesome
and you should be listening to them and
you
give away your own your own capacity for
inner checking and experience
and yeah and then if you mix in
uh if you mix in uh sexuality in the
midst
in the mix which has to do with
well you know stuff like self do selfish
desire and all of that stuff
this slide is just so simple i mean it
happens
just statistically over time you're
going to slide into situations where
uh people misuse their standing in power
in this extremely intimate connection
and extremely hierarchical connection
which it naturally becomes
to fulfill their own sexual
gratification
at the expense of a profound violation
of another
uh person's integrity uh so
it's just a very very simple way of
saying it
is uh we don't as social beings
these energies are so strong and so
powerful
that if we don't contain them and spread
them out
and decentralize them the wires blow up
we we just put too much energy in the
wire
blows up right um
so so that's the first part but the
second part
um about um
you actually wrote this down right um
yes can we work from iran from
transcendence towards iran this is
actually yes um so on the one hand
we should keep this this transcendent
scale
in mind but on the other
uh we should also be in um
we should also be aware of we have these
four quadrants right
so um by going
into for instance the causal and
meditating on that a lot
whether passing or whatnot
we can um
we can have a leverage point from which
we can access a more direct experience
of the deeper layers and from there on
change things at the lower layers
but there there's nothing automatic
about that
so uh so we can also risk doing a
spiritual bypassing when we do so
meaning that um
[Music]
well if our traumas are too big
and too hidden to us and we're too
unaware of them
uh like no mind-blowing
psychedelic experience is gonna help
uh to to get past them we actually have
to wrestle the lower states and so i
know
um so
yes we can it's more like an instrument
we can play it right
uh we have to find the keys and find the
melodies on it so
it all depends on where we're at and
sometimes we have to go a little bit
higher to go a little bit lower
sometimes you have to go a lot higher to
go a lot lower sometimes we have to go
really really deep down to be careful to
back up
so it's a more dynamic process and i
think
that would be my intuition as well um
just saying that we shouldn't opt for
either or that uh either the
transcendent or the descent
or either the ascender or the trans
descender
spirituality we should view them as uh
interconnected and uh and always
always working together and
each of them set natural limits for the
other
so if we travel the states
[Music]
well spirals are popular right
so if we're we start in the matrix
and then at the seven it's somewhat
somewhat uneasy and we travel up and
down a little bit
we this spiritual path um
is usually a kind of a kind of
spiral that spirals out of that right
uh so we go up to the more transcendent
we go down
uh to the more visceral
and and uh and painful uh we
we work through very very real and
emotional
and relational stuff which can bring us
up to the more
universal again that might put
new things within the vicinity of our
capacities to recognize things within
ourselves
or or set us in new relationships where
we have to deal with
even software problems and so on
yeah thank you christian very good
questions um i
i think i gave a somewhat meandering
answer but
i hope i i'm pointing to something
cool question did you have any follow-up
uh
well i was we're pretty much at the end
of the session right
yeah i think um if if daniel is okay
with it we have like one or two more
questions if that's cool
yeah well i would i'd like to kind of
as a follow-up tie this into peter's
question about communitas
and the sangha and
how um
a communitas or like you know a a coming
together of people
as a possible way to
you know explore uh our eroticism and
our transcendence and all this
can be done like is there uh what have
we learned from the past maybe
that will inform the way we come
together so that we don't
form cults um is there some type of like
you know decentralized way that this is
going to happen that you know
prevents that what are your thoughts on
that idea
yeah so so we're getting into the
into um the topic of future religion
right
um but yes uh it's
something in the in the direction of
democratizing
the guru becomes
maybe a little bit more fictional but we
admit that it's fictional
just kind of like we're admitting that
god is fictional that's what
alexander bart and his friend uh
john arguing in this book right uh
cynthia's
that we have to create god from scratch
again and again in the internet age
um and in the same way we have to
recreate the sangha
in a way that is democratizing
now that is a very very very difficult
thing to do
for this reason eroticism
um has to do with transcendence and
and ascendance but also has to do with
exceptionality
with chosenness um with specialness
right
uh and also actually with submission
and and and uh and power
so the sexiest of the ideologies
uh political ideologies is fascism uh
because uh and i mean this is
we might not think that but
when we see our elected politicians
we don't scream at them as if they were
rock stars
and fantasize about them at home uh but
that is what happened
when fascist leaders came to power
because the power is sexy and hierarchy
is sexy and spurs eroticism
whereas democracy is uh
well it's the bland nice guy
and um diffusing power
is inherently unsexy
and we can't help ourselves from from
this uh from this dynamic
nevertheless then we have to create
a democratized spirituality we have to
deal with
this inherent uh
with this inherent paradox
so i mean i think you really nailed it
we have to democratize your child we
have to decentralize
this spiritual authority we have to make
it more
shared and experiential and exploratory
and i think the way to do that is a lot
through
what we talked about last time in
aesthetics
to create these transcendent aesthetics
at the crossroads of fact and fiction
um and and gather around those
and i guess a positive example i i mean
certainly not one without its problems
but it is
the burning man culture in the sense
that people are coming together
they're there as equals in many regards
at least
and they create artwork together
and interact in a
in a setting where you try to lock out
the the hierarchies of
the world outside however
all of that is dependent on a fairly
high
threshold where people who show up there
already are interesting people they're
abundant in different in different
ways and uh and and
uh often uh sexually attractive and so
on and
people who aren't might be less inclined
to show up there
so um um
so i mean can we can we stretch
our eroticism um can we
become more open to new experiences
um not necessarily in the sexual sense
but uh just in the general sense
more open to appreciating one another
and thus
creates like and i think hierarchies are
important here
but i think the more multimodal our
hierarchies are
the more democratic they are so so that
we can admire
different qualities in one another and
then have um
like the tools to see those different
strings
and be blown away by each other
because that's ultimately what it's uh
what it's about
uh so so we don't want a situation where
everybody is sitting in the sangha
and this stuff literally happens in a
place in portugal
and they then they sing about how much
they want to kiss the feet of the guru
and the guru just sits there and nods
and there's something profoundly sick
about that of course
uh we should be kissing the feet of just
any other person
um because we think they're so awesome
no we shouldn't kiss me
that's silly but uh yeah but you see
what i mean that
um that somehow
we need and to well these these five
qualities and the last one is opening up
the more we open up the more we can open
up to
uh different uh interesting
unique genuinely powerful qualities of
one another
and and that's kind of the things we
have to create rituals and structures
for
so i don't have the answers here but i
think the direction is
fairly clear exploratory
the deep co-created um
spiritual sanghas which are perhaps
much more modal and much less
rigid in their structures still creates
a lot of
a lot of space for faults
sure the point is that we would have
shorter feedback cycles so we can
correct the faults or correct the errors
uh more quickly and self-correct
um
yeah so the relation of tomorrow would
probably be something in that direction
great great response i appreciate that
thanks
awesome fascinating thank you so much i
think uh that's gonna have to be our
last question
uh because we're out of time uh daniel
did you have anything to close us out
with
this thing that didn't make it into the
into this one
into the powerpoint just um
qualities and these come in a hierarchy
so going more directly for transcendence
one of the most powerful meditations uh
is awareness meditation a very direct
form of awareness meditation
which i feel marries these qualities of
transcendence
and uh ascendance and it's
an open eye meditation
and as you sit down with open eyes and
you look at stuff i don't know who
invented this
i came across the ring of course a while
ago
and and you sit down and you grab
a nice object hopefully nicer than this
one
and um and you look at it very closely
and and then you look for the quality of
perfection
and once you've found details like
subtle little details in it then you
look for the quality
of delight in yourself
over that perfection
and after a while when you've delighted
at
the color of this thing
how it shines etcetera glass these are
actually pretty fascinating
then you can have a sense of wonder and
that's the third quality
and once and if you've been in the sense
of wonder for a while
and this only happens every now and then
but i i can see it on
on the eeg meter that i get a spike in
in gamma waves
you get a sense of euphoric happiness it
just kind of flows up
through you and in that
euphoric happiness once you've sat there
and
looked for a little while with that you
have the sense of equanimity
and imperative imperturbability and
nothing can move you because you are
already
euphorically happy and
when you have equanimity
and imperturbability ability then
is
then there is a space for of safety
and you just feel a basic
safety or okayness
and once you're safe that's
when you start to have a quality of
innocence
just direct childlike innocence
and in that sense of innocence
you sit there and you're innocently
enjoying
the safety and safety the the perfection
the
light the wonder the foreign happiness
you're equanimous
you feel safe feel innocent
then there is a sense of immediacy
that just is-ness or being
it takes you perhaps to stage 11
vast open
and that's well cartel has this power of
nothing
and i think he he emphasizes
the power of an albert prematurely
um because the power of now it's not
going to be there
unless we have the safety so
and actually all of the other qualities
so uh i uh
posit that in the future
forms of aesthetically driven
spirituality will uh
partake in this kind of open eye
meditation
and uh and travel through these
qualities
and from and particularly then the most
difficult of all which is
safety and then safety
is uh actually where we can play and be
innocent together
um so so that that's kind of my vision
for for the future of
spirituality and i think if this
meditation i don't know who invented it
but i think it's absolutely genius
awesome fascinating uh practical tips
for us
here we do like our practices here at
stoa
so uh thanks so much daniel we'll see
him again same time next week
coming up in about 15 minutes or so
maybe 10 minutes jillian richardson will
be here to discuss
community during covid and how to create
an unlonely planet
i'll drop the link to rsvp in the chat
so yeah thanks again daniel thank you
everybody for coming
thanks guys thanks y'all
you